A Finding Aid to the Gertrude Abercrombie papers, circa 1880-1986, bulk 1935-1977, in the Archives of American Art AAA.abergert
Archives of American Art
Gertrude Abercrombie papers
bulk 1935-1977
circa 1880-1986
AAA.abergert
Archives of American Art
5.7 Linear feet
The papers of surrealist artist Gertrude Abercrombie date from circa 1880-1986, with the bulk of the material dated 1935-1977, and measure 5.7 linear feet. Found within are biographical material; correspondence (mostly incoming letters) with friends, museums, and galleries; files for artists that interested her; writings and notes, including five journal-type notebooks; scattered personal business records; two sketchbooks by Abercrombie and additional sketches and drawings, some by others; printed material, audio recordings, one scrapbook, photographs, and estate records.
Abercrombie, Gertrude, 1909-1977
Provenance
Donald Baum, executor of both the estate and trust of Gertrude Abercrombie, donated the papers to the Archives of American Art in 1978 and 1986.
Related Material
A photograph of Gertrude Abercrombie at home with her painting "Slaughter House", was donated by Donald Baum to the National Collection of Fine Arts in 1979 and transferred to the Archives of American Art that same year.
Alternative Forms Available
A portion of the collection is available on microfilm reels 1429-1435, and for interlibrary loan. The arrangement on microfilm may differ from the current arrangement.
Restrictions on Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Biographical Note
Surrealist painter Gertrude Abercrombie (1909-1977) lived and worked in Chicago and was a prominent member of Chicago's Hyde Park arts community.
Abercrombie was known for surrealist oil paintings featuring dreamlike landscapes and fantasies. Her wide circle of friends included locally and nationally known artists, writers, and jazz musicians who made her home a popular avant-garde salon. She was the inspiration for Richie Powell's "Gertrude's Bounce" and, appeared as a fictional character in Malcolm, Eustace Chisholm, and as herself in Gertrude of Stony Island Avenue all by James Purdy.
The only child of Tom and Lula Janes [Jane] Abercrombie, Gertrude was born in Austin, Texas in 1909, while her opera singer parents were in town with a traveling company. In 1913, the family relocated to Berlin to further Jane's career, but the outbreak of World War I forced their return to the United States. They lived with Tom Abercrombie's family in Alledo, Illinois, before permanently settling in Chicago.
Gertrude Abercrombie had a facility with language and possessed musical and artistic talents. After graduation from the University of Illinois at Champaign-Urbana with a degree in romance languages in 1929, she studied figure drawing at the School of the Art Institute of Chicago for a short time. She then enrolled at the American Arcademy of Art, also in Chicago, for a year long course in commercial art. Her first job was drawing gloves for Mesirow Department Store ads, followed by a stint working as an artist for Sears.
By 1932, Gertrude Abercrombie began painting seriously. The following summer, she participated in an outdoor art fair in downtown Chicago where she made her first sale and received favorable mention in a newspaper review of the event. Abercrombie's work that featured self-portraits and recurring images of personal symbols - trees, horses, owls, keys, shells, doors, stairways, ladders - began to attract attention. Beginning in 1934, Gertrude Abercrombie was employment as a painter in the WPA Federal Art Project in 1934, enabling her to feel validated as an artist and move from the home of her conservative, Christian Scientist parents to her own apartment. The Chicago Society of Artists presented a solo exhibition of Abercrombie's work in 1934, and in 1936 she showed at the Katharine Kuh Gallery (along with Rita Stein and Nicola Ziroli). In 1936 and 1938 Gertrude Abercrombie won prizes at the Art Institute of Chicago's Annual Exhibition of Works by Artists of Chicago and Vicinity.
She left the WPA in 1940 and married lawyer Robert Livingston. Their daughter, Dinah, was born in 1942, and they soon moved to a large Victorian house on South Dorchester St. where Gertude lived for the remainder of her life. The couple divorced in 1948. That same year she married Frank Sandiford, a music critic whose pen name was Paul Warren. An accomplished improvisational pianist, Gertrude Abercrombie became friends with many prominent jazz artists whom she met through Sandiford; in fact, Dizzy Gillespie performed at their wedding. Abercrombie and Sandiford separated in 1964.
The 1940s through 1950s were Gertrude Abercrombie's most productive and prolific period. Although she no longer painted many portraits, he work remained focused on the same themes and symbols. She believed that art was about ideas rather than technique and insisted that "It is always myself that I paint." During this period, Amercrombie exhibited widely in group shows and had solo exhibitions at the Art Institute of Chicago, Associated American Artists (New York), and Leonard Linn, Inc. (Winnetka, Ill.)
By the late 1950s, Gertrude Abercrombie began a long decline. Alcoholism started to take a toll. She suffered serious financial reverses, and in 1964 separated from Frank Sandiford. Debilitating arthritis eventually landed her in a wheel chair, and she became reclusive. In 1977, very near the end of her life, Gertrude Abercrombie was honored with a well-received retrospective exhibition at the Hyde Park Art Center, Chicago. She was able to attend the reception and enjoy seeing the many old friends who were at the event.
Gertrude Abercrombie died in Chicago in 1977. Her will established The Gertrude Abercrombie Trust that cared for and distributed to various institutions her own paintings and a personal collection of works by other artists to selected institutions, mainly in the Midwest.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of surrealist artist Gertrude Abercrombie date from circa 1880-1986, with the bulk of the material dated 1935-1977, and measure 5.7 linear feet. Found within the papers are biographical material; correspondence (mostly incoming letters) with friends, museums, and galleries; artists files; writings and notes, including five journal-type notebooks; scattered personal business records; two sketchbooks by Abercrombie and additional sketches and drawings, some by others; printed material, audio recordings, one scrapbook, photographs, and estate records.
Biographical material consists of biographical notes, Gertrude Abercrombie's will, address books, and a file titled "memorabilia." Personal and professional correspondence consists mainly of incoming letters and some drafts of Gertrude Abercrombie's outgoing letters. Letters from museums and galleries concern loans of paintings and exhibitions. A large amount of the personal correspondence consists of post cards including many antique ones, as well as cards containing original art work by Julio de Diego, Jerry [Jerome] Karidis, Karl Priebe.
Artist files consist of correspondence, printed material, and photographs concerning painters, writers, a jazz musician, and a photographer. The individuals represented are: Dudley Huppler, Jerome Karidis, Karl Priebe, James Purdy, Sonny Rollins, Carl Van Vechten, Wendell Wilcox, John Wilde, and Thornton Wilder.
Writings and notes include reminiscences, miscellaneous writings and notes, and a girlhood diary with brief entries. Five notebooks contain a variety of writings dating from 1953 through 1975, and undated. One volume concerns only her second husband Frank Sandiford.
Business records include a painting catalog on file cards, mailing and guest lists, and miscellaneous sales records. In addition, six notebooks record expenses, sales, inventories, mailing lists, a register of paintings, and a guest book.
There are two sketchbooks, Christmas card designs, sketches and drawings done by Gertrude Abercrombie. There are also prints, drawings, and a painting by Emil Arman, B. Evans, de Diego, and unknown artists.
Printed material consists of articles and clippings about Gertrude Abercrombie, exhibition catalogs, and reproductions. Also included are books by friends inscribed by the authors, among them: Nelson Algren, Richard Armour, Dudley Huppler, James Purdy, Ned Rorem, Paul Warren [pen name of Abercrombie's second husband, Frank Sandiford], Studs Terkel, and Thornton Wilder.
Audio recordings (33-1/3 rpm phonograph alums) are inscribed to Gertrude Abercrombie by the artists. Orlando's album cover, designed by Abercrombie, incorporates one of her paintings.
Records of the Estate of Gertrude Abercrombie and the Gertrude Abercrombie Trust, Donald Baum, Executor, consist mainly of correspondence with the institutions that were offered works of art by Gertrude Abercrombie and from her personal collection. Also included are general correspondence, financial and tax records, and legal documents.
There is one scrapbook dated 1943 containing photographs and printed material.
Photographs are of art work, people, places, and miscellaneous subjects; negatives, slides, and transparencies are included in this series, too. Photographs of art include the work of Gertrude Abercrombie, Karl Priebe, and Charles Sebree. People pictured are Gertrude Abercrombie and family, including her parents, Richard I. Livingston, Dinah Livingston, and Frank Sandiford. There are also 19th and early 20th century photographs of ancestors. Among the images of friends are: Ivan le Lorraine Albright, Arnold Blanch, Dudley Huppler, Doris Lee, Karl Priebe, and Richard Purdy. Photographs of jazz artists include: Louis Armstrong, George Davis, Erroll Garner, Dizzy Gillespie, Earl Hines, Orlando, Charlie Parker, Sonny Rollins, Sarah Vaughn, and the Modern Jazz Quartet. Of particular note the portraits of Gertrude Abercrombie and Dizzy Gillespie by Carl Van Vechten.Among the photographs of places are interior views of Gertrude Abercrombie's home and studio, unidentified landscapes, travel pictures of San Francisco and commercially produced stereopticon slides of other locations. Miscellaneous subjects are automobiles, cats, exhibition installations, and a still life setup.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into 11 series:
Series 1: Biographical Material, circa 1902-1976 (Box 1, OV9; 0.1 linear ft.)
Series 2: Correspondence, circa 1935-1977 (Boxes 1-2; 1.65 linear ft.)
Series 3: Artist files, circa 1935-1977 (Box 2; 0.25 linear ft.)
Series 4: Writings and Notes, circa 1919-1977 (Box 3; 0.1 linear ft.)
Series 5: Business Records, circa 1944-1977 (Box 3; 0.2 linear ft.)
Series 6: Art Work, circa 1939-1975 (Boxes 3, 7; O.2 linear ft.)
Series 7: Printed Material, circa 1906-1977 (Boxes 3-4; 1.6 linear ft.)
Series 8: Audio Recordings, circa 1970-1974 (Box 7; 0.1 linear ft.)
Series 9: Estate Records, circa 1976-1986 (Box 5; o.5 linear ft.)
Series 10: Scrapbook, circa 1943(Box 5; 1 folder)
Series 11: Photographs, circa 1880-1978(Boxes 5-7; OV8, 1.0 linear ft.)
Algren, Nelson, 1909-1981; Amour, Richard; Arman, Emil; De Diego, Julio, 1900-; Evans, B.; Huppler, Dudley, 1917-1988; Karidis, Jerome; Priebe, Karl J., 1914-1976; Purdy, James; Rollins, Sonny; Rorem, Ned, 1923-; Terkel, Studs, 1912-2008; Van Vechten, Carl, 1880-1964; Warren, Paul, 1916-; Wilcox, Wendell; Wilde, John, 1919-; Wilder, Thornton, 1897-1975; Diaries; Drawings; Photographs; Scrapbooks; Sketchbooks; Sketches; Sound recordings; Surrealism; Writings
- Biographical Material, circa 1902-1976; Series 1; 0.1 Linear feet Box 1, OV 9
  Scope and Contents note
  Biographical material consists of biographical notes, Gertrude Abercrombie's will, address books, and a file titled "memorabilia." Among the memorabilia are: the wedding announcement of Gertrude Abercrombie and Robert I. Livingston; daughter Dinah Livingston's childhood letters and greeting cards to her mother, along with school records; miscellaneous printed material includes a newspaper clipping about the Aledo championship football team of 1900, of which Gertrude's father, Tom Abercrombie, was a member.
  - Addresses, undated; (3 vols. and loose slips) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Biographical Notes, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Chicago City Council Tribute to Gertrude Abercrombie, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Memorabilia, 1902-1967, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Stock Certificate, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Will, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Certificate and Diplomas, 1921-1929 (Box OV 9)
- Correspondence, circa 1935-1977; Series 2; 1.65 Linear feet Boxes 1-2
  Personal and professional correspondence consists mainly of incoming letters and some drafts of Gertrude Abercrombie's outgoing letters. Letters from museums and galleries concern loans of paintings and exhibitions. A large amount of the personal correspondence consists of post cards including many antique ones, and cards containing original art work by Julio de Diego, Jerry [Jerome] Karidis, Karl Priebe.
  - Correspondence (Anderson-Williams; unidentified, Alice-Reg), undated (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
  - Correspondence, 1935-1965, undated (Box 1, Folder 9-28)
  - Correspondence, 1966-1977 (Box 2, Folder 1-16)
  - Greeting Cards, 1950-1977 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Artist files, circa 1935-1977; Series 3; 0.25 Linear feet Box 2
  Artist files consist of correspondence, printed material, and photographs concerning painters, writers, a jazz musician, and a photographer. The individuals represented are: Dudley Huppler, Jerome Karidis, Karl Priebe, James Purdy, Sonny Rollins, Carl Van Vechten, Wendell Wilcox, John Wilde, and Thornton Wilder. Additional letters from many of these people are included with correspondence (Series 1).
  - Huppler, Dudley, 1950-1971, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Karidis, Jerome, 1951-1977, undated (Box 2, Folder 19-20)
  - Priebe, Karl, 1940-1976, undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Purdy, James, 1953-1977, undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Rollins, Sonny, 1962-1975 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Van Vechten, Carl, 1950-1956 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Wilcox, Wendell, 1947-1975, undated (Box 2, Folder 25-26)
  - Wilde, John, 1951-1968, undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Wilder, Thornton, 1935-1975, undated (Box 2, Folder 28)
- Writings and Notes, circa 1919-1977; Series 4; 0.1 Linear feet Box 3
  Among the writings and notes are a girlhood diary with brief entries, reminiscences, miscellaneous writings and notes. Notebooks contain a variety of writings: Vol. 1: 1953-1959, includes income and expenses, quips, reminiscences, miscellaneous notes; Vol. 2: 1959 is a brief journal; Vol. 3: 1971-1975 includes reminiscences; Vol. 4: undated, features lists of cats, roomers, names and addresses; and Vol. 5: undated, is about Frank Sandiford, her second husband.
  - Diary, 1919; 1924; (1 vol.) (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Writings and Notes, 1963, 1975, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Notebooks, 1953-1959, 1971-1977, undated; (5 vols.) (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Business Records, circa 1944-1977; Series 5; 0.2 Linear feet Box 3
  Business Records: Vol. 1: 1949 (expenses, sales, inventory, profit and loss, mailing lists); Vol. 2: 1950-1959 (painting register); Vol. 3: 1950-1966 (sales register); Vol. 4: 1952-1957 (paintings exhibited); Vol. 5: 1957 ("Fall Opening" guest register); Vol. 6: 1969-1970 (sales at shows)
  - Business Records, 1949-1969; (6 vols.) (Box 3, Folder 4-5)
  - Catalog File of Paintings (Box 3)
    - Out; In Studio, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Disposed Of (includes sales), undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Sales [folded sheets in Catalog File], undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Gilman Galleries, 1964, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Mailing Lists and Guest Lists, 1977, undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Art Work, circa 1939-1975; Series 6; 0.2 Linear feet Boxes 3, 7
  Art work by Gertrude Abercrombie consists of two sketchbooks, Christmas card designs, sketches and drawings. There are also prints, drawings, and a painting by Emil Arman, B. Evans, de Diego, and unknown.
  - By Gertrude Abercrombie (Box 3)
    - Christmas Card Designs, 1939, undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
      - Sketchbook, undated; (1 vol.; see also: Box 7) (Box 3, Folder 12)
      - Sketches and Drawings, 1940-1957, undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - By Other Artists - Prints, Drawings, and Painting (Emil arman, B. Evans, Naomi Khrson, and unknown), 1975, undated; ( see also: Box 7) (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - By Gertrude Abercrombie - Sketchbook; By Other Artists - Print (de Diego), undated; (disbound volume, original collation) (Box 7, Folder 1)
- Printed Material, circa 1906-1977; Series 7; 1.6 Linear feet Boxes 3-4
  Printed material consists of articles and clippings about Gertrude Abercrombie, exhibition catalogs, and reproductions. Also included are books by friends inscribed by the authors, among them: Nelson Algren, Richard Armour, Dudley Huppler, James Purdy, Ned Rorem, Paul Warren [pen name of Abercrombie's second husband, Frank Sandiford], Studs Terkel, and Thornton Wilder
  - Articles about/mentioning Gertrude Abercrombie, 1946-1976 (Box 3, Folder 15-16)
  - Books - Inscribed by Authors, 1939-1974; (26 vols.) (Box 3, Folder 17)
    Algren, Nelson. The Neon Wilderness (2 photographs enclosed), 1968
    Armour, Richard. Drugstore Days, 1959
    Armour, Richard. Going Like Sixty, 1974
    Blake, James. The Joint (clipping enclosed), 1971
    Campbell, Gladys. The Momentary Beach, 1972
    Cocreau, Jean. The Difficulty of Being (introduction by Ned Rorem; post card enclosed), 1957
    Huppler, Dudley. The Lesson Book, 1946
    Huppler, Dudley. The New Joker, 1961
    Mezzrow, Milton "Mezz" and Bernard Wolfe. Really the Blues, 1946
    Purdy, James. Cabot Wright Begins, 1964
    Purdy, James. Eustace Chisholm and the Works, 1968
    Purdy, James. The House of the Solitary Maggot, 1974
    Purdy, James. Jeremy's Version, 1970
    Purdy, James. Malcolm, 1959
    Purdy, James. Malcolm [French edition], 1971
    Purdy, James. The Nephew, 1960
    Purdy, James. The Running Sun, 1971
    Purdy, James. 63: Dream Palace, 1956
    Rorem, Ned. The Paris Diary of Ned Rorem (post card enclosed), 1966 (see also: Cocteau, Jean)
  - Books - Inscribed by Authors, 1939-1974 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    Russell, Ross. Bird Lives!, 1973
    Sandiford, Frank ( see: Warren, Paul [pen name])
    Tarcov, Oscar. Bravo My Monster, 1953
    Terkel, Studs. Giants of Jazz, 1957
    Turbyfill, Mark. A Marriage with Space (commentary by Turbyfill enclosed), 1973
    Warren, Paul. The Next Time Is For Life, [1953]
    Wilder, Thornton. Heaven's My Destination, 1935, 1960 (2 copies [one paperback])
  - Books - Inscribed by Others, 1930-1939; (26 vols.) (Box 4, Folder 2)
    Stein, Gertrude. Picasso (inscribed by Warren), 1939
    Works in Progress, Number 1 (includes contributions by Algren and Purdy; inscribed by Helen), 1970
  - Books - Not Inscribed (History of the Hyde Park Art Center 1939-1976) (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Clippings (Box 4)
    - Gertrude Abercrombie, undated (Box 4, Folder 4-5)
    - Gertrude Abercrombie, 1954-1979 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Artists, 1933-1974, undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Jazz, 1948-1975, undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Miscellaneous Art Topics, 1968-1977, undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Miscellaneous Subjects (not art related), 1938-1973, undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Exhibition Catalogs and Announcements, 1932-1977, undated (Box 4, Folder 11-18)
  - Exhibition Catalogs (not Gertrude Abercrombie), 1936-1976, undated (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Items, 1906-1951, undated (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Periodicals (Box 4)
    - Arsenal: Surrealist Subversion (no. 3), 1976 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - The Living Museum, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Manuscript (April 1935 and April 1936 issues contain pieces by Wendell Wilcox), 1935-1936 (Box 4, Folder 23-25)
  - Postcards (blank), undated (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Reproductions [from magazines and lecture programs], 1937-1973, undated (Box 4, Folder 27-28)
- Audio Recordings, circa 1970-1974; Series 8; 0.1 Linear feet Box 7
  All recordings are 33-1/3 rpm phonograph alums inscribed to Gertrude Abercrombie by the artists. Orlando's album cover, designed by Abercrombie, incorporates one of her paintings.
  - Cain, Jackie and Roy Kral. "Time and Love" and "A Wilder Alias", 1972, circa 1974 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Gillespie, Dizzy. "Dizzy on the French Rivera", undated (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Orlando. "Orlando!...", 1970 (Box 7, Folder 4)
- Estate Records, circa 1976-1986; Series 9; 0.5 Linear feet Box 5
  Records of the Estate of Gertrude Abercrombie and the Gertrude Abercrombie Trust, Donald Baum, Executor, consist mainly of correspondence with institutions being offered works of art by Gertrude Abercrombie and from her personal art collection. In addition, general correspondence, financial and tax records, and legal documents are included.
  - Correspondence, General (Box 5, Folder 1-3)
  - Correspondence with Auction House (Henzel Galleries, Inc.), 1977-1980 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence with Conservator Barry R. Bauman, 1979-1980 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence with Institutions, 1875-1885 (Box 5, Folder 6-28)
    Auckland Memorial Art Center, 1980
    Art Institute of Chicago, Prints and Drawings Department, 1978-1979
    Art Institute of Chicago, Twentieth Century Painting and Sculpture Department, 1978
    Beinecke Library, Yale University, 1980
    Detroit Institute of Arts, 1979
    Elmhurst College, 1979-1980
    Essley Noble Memorial Museum, 1979
    Illinois State Museum, 1979
    Illinois State University, Center for Visual Arts Gallery, 1979
    Indianapolis Museum of Art, 1978
    Krannert Art Museum, University of Illinois, 1978-1979
    Lakeview Museum of Arts and Sciences, 1978
    Madison Art Center, Inc., 1978-1979
    Milwaukee Art Center, 1978-1979
    Museum of Contemporary Art (Chicago), 1978-1979
    National Baseball Hall of Fame and Museum, 1979
    National Collection of Fine Arts, Smithsonian Institution, 1978
    National Portrait Gallery, Smithsonian Institution, 1978-1980
    Smart Gallery, University of Chicago, 1978-1979
    Southern Illinois University Museum and Art Gallery, 1979
    University of Michigan Art Museum, 1979
    Western Illinois University Art Gallery, 1978-1979
    Whitney Museum of American Art, 1978-1979
  - Financial Records, 1977-1984, undated (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Inventories, 1977-1980, undated (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Legal Documents, 1976-1980 (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Notes, undated (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - Tax Returns, 1977-1984 (Box 5, Folder 33)
- Scrapbook, circa 1943; Series 10; 0.2 Linear feet Box 5
  The scrapbook contains photographs of works by Gertrude Abercrombie and a small amount of printed material consisting of reviews and pages from exhibition catalogs.
  - Scrapbook (1 vol. disbound), 1943, undated (Box 5, Folder 34)
- Photographs, circa 1880-1978; Series 11; 1 Linear feet Boxes 5-7; OV 8
  Photographs are of art work, people, places, and miscellaneous subjects; negatives, slides, and transparencies are included in this series, too.
  Photographs of art include the work of Gertrude Abercrombie, Karl Priebe, and Charles Sebree.
  People pictured are Gertrude Abercrombie and family, including her parents, Richard I. Livingston, Dinah Livingston, and Frank Sandiford. There are also 19th and early 20th century photographs of ancestors. Among the images of friends are: Ivan le Lorraine Albright, Arnold Blanch, Dudley Huppler, Doris Lee, Karl Priebe, and Richard Purdy. Photographs of jazz artists include: Louis Armstrong, George Davis, Erroll Garner, Dizzy Gillespie, Earl Hines, Orlando, Charlie Parker, Sonny Rollins, Sarah Vaughn, and the Modern Jazz Quartet. Of particular note the portraits of Gertrude Abercrombie and Dizzy Gillespie by Carl Van Vechten.